<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://localhost:4000/assets/xslt/rss.xslt" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://localhost:4000/assets/css/rss.css" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Wael Farah</title>
		<description>Dr. Wael Farah | SETI Institute</description>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
		<atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Detecting Voyager 1 with the ATA</title>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/blog/voyager1/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
				<description>&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;medium-4 medium-push-8 columns&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;panel radius&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p id=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-refurbishment-of-the-allen-telescope-array&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-refurbishment-of-the-allen-telescope-array&quot;&gt;The refurbishment of the Allen Telescope Array&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#observations&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data-analysis&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-data-analysis&quot;&gt;Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#link-budget-calculation&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-link-budget-calculation&quot;&gt;Link budget calculation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- /.medium-4.columns --&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;medium-8 medium-pull-4 columns&quot;&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Almost 45 years after its launch, Voyager 1 is the farthest human-made object from our home planet. 
Located 156 AU, or 23.3 billion km, (at the time of writing) away in the direction of the constellation Ophiuchus, 
Voyager 1, along with its twin Voyager 2, is set on a mission to explore the boundaries of the 
heliosphere and the interstellar medium. Communications with the space probe is still 
underway using large dishes of the Deep Space Network, and commands/data are sent back 
and forth between earth and Voyager 1, most of the time at a rate of 40 bits per second.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This write-up describes the observation and detection of the Voyager 1 carrier 
signal using the Allen Telescope Array.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-refurbishment-of-the-allen-telescope-array&quot;&gt;The refurbishment of the Allen Telescope Array&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Allen Telescope Array is an interferometer hosted at the Hat Creek Radio Observatory, some 5-hour drive north of San Francisco. The telescope comprises 42 fully-steerable 6.1m-diameter telescopes, of which ~20 are fitted with wideband cryogenically cooled feeds. The feeds sense electromagnetic waves within the frequency range of 1 to 12 GHz. A refurbishment program has been underway since early 2019 aimed at upgrading the feeds along with the digital signal processing hardware and software. As part of the ongoing refurbishment, a new digital correlator and beamformer based on commodity CPUs and GPUs is being developed and installed.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../assets/img/ATA2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;ATA&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Allen Telescope Array (Credit: Joe Marfia)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;A beamformer, in the recieving paradigm, is the process of coherently summing
multiple receptors in order to maximize their sensitivity towards a particular 
spatial direction. Beamforming is a very rich topic and I won’t go into details 
here, but in short, a beamformer requires a calibration scheme to compute the 
instrumental delays and phases (with respect to a reference) of each station 
of an array. For the ATA beamformer system, we utilize a correlator – a software 
suit that multiplies signals from each pair of antennas together – to derive the 
needed delay and phase solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2 id=&quot;observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On July 9th, 2022, the 20 available antennas of the Allen Telescope Array were used to 
observe the Voyager 1 space probe. The coherent downlink frequency of Voyager 1, in the X-band, 
is ~8420.43 MHz, with a spectral width of &amp;lt;1 Hz. The ATA was tuned at a center 
frequency of 8400 MHz (the beamformer’s bandwidth is relatively large, 672 MHz). 
No DSN observations were underway at the the time of the ATA observation, 
therefore I assume no two-way communication mode has been set, and the transponder 
is not locked to the uplink frequency.
Ten minutes of data on a nearby quasar were collected using the correlator, 
and a delay/phase solution was derived for the beamformer. The antennas were then 
pointed at the position of Voyager 1 as determined using the ephemeris obtained 
from the solar system dynamics NASA/JPL &lt;a href=&quot;https://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/horizons/app.html&quot;&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;
(ICRF RA = 17:13:41.13, Dec = +12:23:49.9). Fifteen minutes of beamformed complex baseband 
data were then recorded and stored on disk.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2 id=&quot;data-analysis&quot;&gt;Data Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A large, ~500,000 point FFT was applied to the recorded data to bring the spectral resolution to a 
value close to that of the spectral width of the carrier frequency. Due to the fact 
that a changing velocity offset exists between earth and Voyager 1, the received carrier 
frequency will inevitably be Doppler shifted and drifting in time. The Doppler shift 
was then calculated (thanks &lt;a href=&quot;https://destevez.net/&quot;&gt;Danni Estévez&lt;/a&gt;), 
and a waterfall plot of one of polarization was displayed. 
The figure below shows the dynamic spectrum of
the Voyager 1 downlink signal.v&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../assets/img/voyager_waterfall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Voyager1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A waterfall (frequency vs time) plot displaying the Voyager 1 spacecraft 
as seen by the Allen Telescope Array. The color scale represents the flux density in units 
of dB. The narrowband signal is clearly seen drifting in frequency, as expected of a transmitter
accelerating with respect to a receiver.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The data were corrected for the Doppler effect at a drift rate of ~-0.84Hz/s, and 
a carrier-to-noise of 11.5 dB was measured in a single polarization of the recorded 900 second segment.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2 id=&quot;link-budget-calculation&quot;&gt;Link budget calculation&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Voyager 1 is equipped with a Pt = 22.4 W transmitter and it utilizes a Gt = 48 dBi
high gain 
directional antenna pointed straight at earth (to read more about Voyager’s 
specification, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://voyager.gsfc.nasa.gov/Library/DeepCommo_Chapter3--141029.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;). 
The spacecraft, at the time of observation, is at a distance of r = 23.3e9 km 
from earth.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Power density:&lt;/p&gt;

\[P_D = \frac{P_t \times G_t}{4\times\pi\times R^2} 
        = \frac{22.4\times10^{4.8}}{4\times\pi\times (23.3\times10^{12})^{^2}} 
        = 2.07 \times 10^{-22}\,\textrm{W.m}^{-2}\]

    &lt;p&gt;Next, we’ll calculate the received power by the ATA beamformer. We use N_ant = 20 
antennas in our 
observation, each antenna is ~6m in diameter with an aperture efficiency of 
~0.6 in the X-band:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Collecting area:&lt;/p&gt;

\[A = N_{ant} \times \pi \times r^2 \times \epsilon_A = 339.3\,\textrm{m}^2\]

    &lt;p&gt;Power received:&lt;/p&gt;

\[P = P_D \times A = 7.03 \times 10^{-20}\,\textrm{W} = -161.53\,\textrm{dBm}\]

    &lt;p&gt;Next, we’ll calculate the ATA thermal noise:&lt;/p&gt;

\[N_0 = k_B \times T_{rec} \times BW = 1.38\times 10^{-23} \times 120 \times 1 = 
    1.66\times 10^{-21}\,\textrm{W} = -177.81\,\textrm{dBm}\]

    &lt;p&gt;The above assumes a receiver temperature of 120 Kelvin at 8.4 GHz. The 
receiver temperature could have also been measured using the quasar observation, 
but the 120 Kelvin figure is not far from reality given previous measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Finally, the expected carrier-to-noise ratio is:&lt;/p&gt;

\[C/N_0 = P - N_0 = 16.3\,\textrm{dB}\]

    &lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The measured carrier-to-noise ratio in the 900s segment of our ATA data is 
~5dB less than what is 
expected. We suspect his is due to many factors. Firstly, the Voyager 1 downlink polarization 
produced at X-band is 100% circular, whereas the ATA feeds are linearly polarized. 
Receiving circular polarization on linear feeds would entail a 3dB reduction in C/N0. 
Although synthesizing circular polarization using the ATA feeds is possible, it is 
beyond the scope of this work. Moreover, the Voyager 1 signal was only incoherently 
de-Dopplered. In other words, the effect of Doppler shifting within each of FFT channels
was not corrected for. This will introduce some reduction in C/N0. Finally, the beamformer 
was assumed to have perfect efficiency, which is not the case in real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The detection of Voyager 1, the farthest human-made object, with the refurbished 
Allen Telescope Array is an excellent display of the telescope’s capabilities 
and strengths, and a representation of the outstanding hard work put 
by the ATA team since the start of the refurbishment program in 2019&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- /.medium-8.columns --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- /.row --&gt;

</description>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/voyager1/</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
